Zahid Asghar

Professor

Curriculum Vitae

May 2022

School of Economics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad

2011-2013

zasghar@qau.edu.pk

@zahedasghar

Zahidasghar

in Zahid Asghar

About me

I am applied econometrician and statistician with special interests in development economics, making sense of data through Data visualization and have conducted a large number of trainings on data analytics using Excel, STATA, R and EVIEWS. I have expertise in using R, STATA and Excel, and comfortable in using Datawrapper, Tableau, SPSS and EVIEWS for data anlysis. I am actively engaged in playing with data particularly *PovCalnetR*, *PDHS*, *PSLM*, *WDI using R* among many other survey data sets. I have published in gender, food security and other socio-economic issues both in national and international peer reviewed journals. I am keen in having better awareness of development indicators in the society and to contribute to an evidence based decision making in socio-economic policy. I have strengths both in Statistics and Economics

Education

1983-1985	SSC/MATRIC Rawalpindi	Board of Intermediate and Secondary Education
1985-1987	HSSC Lahore	Board of Intermediate and Secondary Education
1987-1990	Bachelor of Sceince Lahore, Pakistan	University of the Punjab
1990-92	Master of Statistics Multan, Pakistan	Bahauddin Zakaraya University
2002-2007	PhD Economics Islamabad, Pakistan	Pakistan Institute of Development Economics

Employment

Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad2018-to-dateProfessor (School of Economics)2018-to-dateDirector (School of Economics)Jan 2019- Jan 2022Registrar2020-2021Associate Professor2015-2018Assistant Professor2002-2011Lecturer1994-2000State Bank of Pakistan

Senior Faculty, National Institute of Banking and Finance
Sultan Qaboos University, Oman Visiting Consultant (2009-10)

Research Projects and Data Consultancy Projects:

Data Analysis of Tax on Services Sector 2012-2022 of Punjab

Data Analyst for Earning Projection Survey of Free-Lancing jobs under IGNITE, Ministry of Finance 2021, Pakistan

Data consultant for Ignite: National Technology Fund, Ministry of Finance 2019-20

Assessing Data requirements for SDGs through key informant interviews and surveys in progress under NRPU of the HEC (Current) Data were extracted from PSLM and HIES from 1998-2015-16 Surveys

Member of the team as a data analyst for a research project for financing agriculturists through a third party instead of Arhtis at NIBAF, State Bank of Pakistan 2011-13

Consultant for a project on Biases in Consumer Price Index (PIDE)

2007

Member of Professional/Statutory Bodies

- ➤ Senate Member, Pakistan Institute of Development Economics 2008-2011
- ➤ Member Research Advisory Council on 'Research for Social Transformation and Advancement' (RASTA) under PSDP of the Ministry of Planning, Development and Special Initiatives, the Government of Pakistan, 2020-21 to-date
- ➤ Member Technical Committee Price Indices , Pakistan Bureau of Statistics 2013 to-date
- ➤ LEAD fellow Cohort-19
- ➤ Member Technical Committee SDGs , Pakistan Bureau of Statistics
- ➤ Member Technical National Account Committee, Pakistan Bureau of Statistics
- ➤ Member, Board of Studies and Faculty at various academic institutions

More than 40 peer reviewed jorunal articles (some are listed below)

- ➤ Shabnam,N, Santeramo,F.,Asghar,Z and Antonio,S "The Impact Of Food Price Crises On The Demand For Nutrients In Pakistan" *Journal of South Asian Development* 11 (3), 305-327
- ➤ Noor, Amna & Asghar, Zahid & Sarwar, Haroon & Arfeen, Irfanullah. (2021). Role of the ICT in Women Empowerment and Achieving SDGs: A Case Study of Women Labor Force in Developing Countries. *ETIKONOMI*. 20. 339-348. 10.15408/etk.v20i2.22045.
- ➤ A Noor, Z Asghar, MI Arfeen, "Role of the ICT in Women's Empowerment and Achieving SDGs 2030: A Case Study of Pakistan by using PDHS Data." *Journal of Managerial Sciences*, 2021
- ➤ Muhammad Asif, Zawar Hussain, Zahid Asghar, Muhammad Irfan Hussain, Mariya Raftab, Said Farooq Shah, Akbar Ali Khan, A statistical evidence of power law distribution in the upper tail of world billionaires' data 2010–20, *Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications*, Volume 581, 2021
- ➤ M Aslam, C Ley, Z Hussain, SF Shah, Z Asghar "A new generator for proposing flexible lifetime distributions and its properties" *PloS One* 15 (4), e0231908 2020
- ➤ Khan, F., Asghar, Z., Tipu, M., Rehman, A., Khan, A., & Rehman, T. "Effect of displacement on Adherence to TB Treatment: An observational study in TB patients from Internally Displaced Persons of Pakistan." *Pakistan Journal of Medical Sciences*, 37(3),2021
- ➤ Asghar, Zahid and Khaild, Mahmood, "Biases in Consumer Price Index Methodology in Pakistan: Suggestions for Improvements" *Pakistan Development Review* Vol.47(3) (2008) 267-285.
- ➤ Musarrat Ijaz, Zahid Asghar & Asma Gul (2019) Ensemble of penalized logistic models for classification of high-dimensional data, *Communications in Statistics Simulation and Computation*, DOI: 10.1080/03610918.2019.1595647
- ➤ Shahzad,M. Riaz, M. and Asghar,Z "On The Evaluation Of Different Forecasters' Performance" Communication in Statistics,Computation and Simulations (2018)

Trainings conducted as a Trainer: (35+ Trainings)

- ➤ Econometrics Using STATA Under TVET Support Program in Pakistan, 2-13 March, 2015
- ➤ Applied Econometrics, NIBAF, State Bank of Pakistan 14-18 December, 2017, Islamabad
- > Data Management and Analysis Using STATA, International Rescue Committee, 25-27 April, 2017 Islamabad
- ➤ Workshop conducted for Mid-Career Management Course on "Data Visualization" Information Services Academy, Islamabad, December, 2020
- ➤ Resource Person for 'Data Visualization and its importance for Journalists and media,' Information Services Academy, Islamabad, 3rd January, 2020
- ➤ Resource Person for Workshop on Applied Economics Using Softwares, School of Economics, QAU, 22-26 July, 2019
- ➤ Resource Person for Workshop on Analysing Data Using Stata, Pakistan Institute of Development Economics, Islamabad, 5-February,2019
- ➤ Data Visualization for Policy Making Using Excel for Faculty Development Program, HEC, 2-Sessions, 20th January, 2019
- ➤ Resource Person for Workshop on Applied Econometrics, School of Economics, QAU, 4-6 Jan, 2019
- ➤ National Invited Speaker for "Making Sense of Data Through Visualization, University of Malakand, Nov-2018
- National Invited Speaker for "Data Visualization," Women University, Multan 11-May, 2018
- > Data, Data Visualization, and Data Driven Decision Making for Faculty Development
- ➤ Program, HEC, 2-Sessions, 20th January, 2017
- ➤ Teaching Basic Statistics for Teachers Workshop at PIDE (Conducted 2 Sessions on
- ➤ Data Visualization and Exploration August, 2016)
- MS Excel-Advanced Young Professional Induction Program Batch 5, NIBAF, State Bank of Pakistan (20-22 June, 2016)
- ➤ Visualization and Exploration of Data Using R for PIDE research staff and students (8-9 May, 2016). Business Intelligence through Financial Modeling-Scenario-Building for Senior

- ➤ Middle Management of SBP-BSC, NIBAF, Islamabad (4 hours), 2016 (2nd Iteration). Business Intelligence through Financial Modeling-Scenario-Building for Senior
- ➤ Middle Management of SBP-BSC, NIBAF, Islamabad (4 hours), 2016
- ➤ Use of Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS) In Agricultural Statistics of Pakistan Ministry of Food Security and Research, PARC, Islamabad Feb.24,2016
- ➤ MS Excel Advanced for SBP-BSC officers at NIBAF Islamabad (Feb.22-23, 2016)
- ➤ Statistical Methods Using STATA for Strengthening of Crops Estimation System in Pakistan by Capacity Building of the Officers. Ministry of Food Security and Research, Islamabad, October 20,2015
- ➤ Applied Research Methods for Economics & Finance, Department of Economics and Finance, PIDE, Islamabad September 7-11,2015
- ➤ Processing and Analysis of Data (Methodology and Software) June10-12, 2015 MS Office-Advanced (Excel, Word & PowerPoint) Young Professional Induction Program. NIBAF, State Bank of Pakistan (22-25 April, 2015)
- ➤ Inflation, Measurement Issues and its Impact on Common Man for Research Officers (Economist Group) M/O Planning, Development and Reform at PPMI, Islamabad (22 Oct, 2014)
- ➤ Data Analysis Using Excel-Advanced for Research Staff and Faculty, Pakistan Institute of Development Economics, Islamabad (9-10 June, 2014)
- ➤ Advanced Applied Econometrics Using STATA/ EVIEWS for State Bank of Pakistan Officers at LRC, Karachi (24 June-5 July 2013)
- lissues in Pakistan Economy, State Bank Officers Training, NIBAF, 6th July, 2013 Islamabad
- ➤ Advanced Econometrics Using STATA and EVIEWS for State Bank of Pakistan Officers (Research, Statistics and Data Ware House wing) at LRC, Karachi (Feb-Mar 2013)
- ➤ Applied Econometrics for State Bank of Pakistan officers (Monetary and Economic Policy Division) at LRC, Karachi (2012)
- Managerial Economics: International Business Administration & IT Course for Central Asian Republics NIBAF, State Bank of Pakistan, (2012)
- National Accounts, State Bank Officers Training Scheme (2012) Biostatistics and Genetic Epidemiology, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad. Served as Focal Person from Aug 02-11 (2016).
- Two weeks training course on Statistics, Planning Commission of Pakistan, Pakistan (2005)
- > Resource Person for Higher Education Commission Faculty Development Program 2017 to-date

PhD thesis

Supervised: 5 Under-progress: 3

Mphil thesis (Supervised): 40 +

References:

Upon request